Your physical presence is fundamental to the way you connect to an audience.
If the way you stand, the way you look, the way you move doesn’t support your message, it will distract and detract from your message.
Think about how you feel when a speaker says, “I’m very excited about the new plan.” You don’t believe them.
We’re expert at reading body language.
So take the time before you speak to prepare yourself physically.
You wouldn’t run onto the sports field without warming up.
You shouldn’t step onto a podium, or step up in a meeting, without preparing physically as well.
What do we mean by physical presence? We mean that combination of body language, of stance, of expression, of gesture
that sends signals to an audience about whether a speaker is confident, whether they’re relaxed, whether they’re credible.
These messages, these unspoken physical messages, have enormous power to influence how an audience reacts to us.
They can undercut our message, however well crafted our words are.
If we aren’t backing that up with a dynamic, energised, confident physical presence,
we’re going to lose the audience. It’s also quite hard, though, because the last thing you want when you’re presenting
is to have part of your being going, “Oh dear, am I fiddling with my fingers?”
And it’s really hard to communicate powerfully if you’re worrying in those ways.
So actually the best way to get rid of those physical distractions is by grounding yourself well in advance.
So feet nice and firmly on the floor. Take some deep breaths in.
Think about calming things that can ground and centre you.
Those kinds of techniques, just before you go in to present or be in a workshop or a meeting, can really help give your physical presence more groundedness
and avoid those little distractions. I’m not saying we all have to look
like a Hollywood actor. We all have our own way of being present. And that’s the important thing you need to do:
find out what your natural style is, and be confident within it.